come back and let's this is let's
complete this distributed scheduleuler
today and this is the last part where I
would be covering the shedlock in depth
okay and this shedlock is like very much
popular in industry as part of doing uh
achieve distributed scheduleular part so
till now what we have seen is that we
have multiple instances
and we handle
we avoid duplication work through
pessimistic log
plus skip
logged feature. Okay,
but there it was that all scheduulers
are working in parallel
and we just avoided the duplication task
with the lock.
But the question is that what if we want
only one instance to work on this
scheduleuler and rest all other
instances should be free and they might
do some other task. Okay, we don't want
to keep every other instance busy with
the scheduleuler job.
So that's where shedlock comes into the
picture. So without shed lock all
instances execute the scheduleuler job
and with pessimistic lock we put lock on
rows to avoid duplicate execution. We
have seen that during uh in the select
query we put for update right.
So we are locking the rows so that no
other can take those low lock on those
row. But with shedlock
only one instance or one pod execute the
scheduleuler job.
So others simply skip the scheduleuler
job execution itself.
Okay. So you can say that here we are
not putting a lock on rows. You can say
that here we are putting a lock on
scheduleuler itself.
So at the scheduleuler itself you can
say that we are putting a lock only one.
We have 100 instances. Only one instance
can acquire the lock on this
scheduleuler. Rest others will escape
it. They don't even wait for it. They
will escape it. Only one instance will
execute the scheduleuler itself. So
there is no locking concept on rows
itself. We are not going to put any lock
on rows.
Now let's see how scheduleuler works. So
before we implement shedlock let's
understand its functionality step by
step and I will also show you the code
part also very important.
So in the shedlock a new table is
created to manage scheduleuler jobs who
is working on what.
So the table name journal is shedlock.
Okay. And the column sets generally
contain four name
the job name. Okay. So right we have uh
have one scheduleuler right scheduled
one job. So you have a method. So with
shedlock we can give a name to each job.
So that is the name
the log that so don't worry about this
when we will see different examples then
this uh columns and all would get more
clear but just one high level uh
introduction you can say that log that
is like let's say you have instance one
instance two instance three instance one
acquired a log on this scheduleuler
which is running at what time logged at
at this point of time let's say 9:00
a.m. I have taken the lock. Consider
that logged until so maximum time
this lock it can cap. So now let's say
for 1 hour
10:00 a.m.
Now you can say that hey what is the
need of putting the lock until if you
have just taken a lock. Okay when when
when you release it then only other will
take. Right? See
there is no physical locking in
shedlock. Consider this that it work on
optimistic locking.
Optimistic locking functionality. No
lock is kept on shedlock and no lock is
kept on rows also. Okay. All is managed
through this two columns itself.
So you logged at 900 a.m. and the logged
until it would be like 10:00 a.m. So you
consider that is the max time the log is
eligible
whoever has logged it logged by. So
let's say instance one has logged it. So
instance one has taken a logged at 9:00
a.m. So when I'm saying that logged at
so don't consider that I'm putting a
actual lock like pessimistic. No, it's
just like a column name which say that
logged at. So everyone will just work on
this one. Hey, you have a logged at
logged until is not yet expired. So
means it is logged. Consider like this
way. So instance one has or I would say
that acquired the lease. So it has
acquired the lease. So it started it put
a started at this time I am acquiring
this job and I will lock until or
acquired the my lease is still this. So
always have
good enough time
that okay it might take 1 hour in max 2
hour in max. So whatever the max
time you want to hold the job you can
add it. I'll show you with examples
multiple use cases that different
scenarios these columns would be used.
So the same four things I have explained
here.
unique name of the job logged at when
some worker thread start working on this
job. Okay, logged until
after this time itself. Log until mean
till this time no one can no other
instance is allowed to pick this job.
After this time any instance is allowed
to acquire execute the job again. Log by
is like identity who the pod and the
method like who
Who acquired this lease? You can say who
acquired the lock.
Okay. Now let's go one level deep. How
this u shedlock works? So shedlock works
m major on interceptor and interceptor
is added. Whenever job schedules time
arrives call goes to interceptor and it
perform task before and after execution
of the job. So consider like this. Okay.
So you have an actual scheduleuler job.
Let's say add the rate schedule
some chron job
and this is my method my job my job.
Now what it does is it create a proxy
scheduleuler job. Shedlock.
What shedlock I say is does it create a
proxy scheduleuler job. Okay. By
creating a child of this scheduleuler
job.
So this is my class. So what it will do
is it will create one another child
class.
Okay. Extend my actual actual
scheduleuler job. It will create one
proxy job which is now a child of my
actual. Okay. And in that what it will
do is that hey job proxy extends a job.
This is the actual one. This is the
proxy one. So it now a child. This proxy
one is the child of the actual one and
it will override the method and in the
override it what it will do is first do
pre-processing
then call the actual job like super dot
run my job. So this actual job right
this has the actual method. So what it
will do is super dot run my job. So it
will invoke the super actual job run it
and after that do some post-processing.
So shedlock works on majorly that hey
whenever instance one instance two
instance three multiple instances
because all have the same code all have
the same code okay and now let's say
your schedule job is to run at 1:00 a.m.
So at 1:00 a.m. every instance will work
right because see code is same we can't
have a different code for this instance
we can't have a different code for this
instance so every instance will get
invoked at let's say 1:00 a.m. that hey
run this job but in shedlock this job is
actually the proxy job you can say and
there we have a pre-processing and
that's where the ultimate work is done
that okay only instance one is allowed
all other instances skip it okay so
we'll see that but all here I want you
to understand that
shedlog create one interceptor or create
one proxy class Okay. And in that proxy
class, it will provide an override the
method,
add some pre-processing,
then run the actual job and add some
post-processing. So this pre-processing
and post-processing understand should be
clear. That's where the most of the
things happens.
And important thing is that for each
scheduleuler job which we want a
shedlock feature in delay Q this proxy
job only get inserted. So you know that
from the first video of the scheduleuler
that delay Q holds the job right. So now
when we are working with the shedlog in
shedlock we know that it creates the
proxy job. So this proxy job ultimately
goes in the shedlock uh delay Q. I'll
show you how. So now this is the overall
flow.
So this is a delayed Q. Let's say
delayed Q and delayed Q has jobs.
Now let's say for any particular job
the time has come.
Notice that this job is a proxy job
means I I have taken a shedlo feature
for it. Okay, for this scheduleuler job
I have taken a shedlock feature and
because of this shedlock feature the
proxy has gone into the delayed queue
not the actual job. Now worker thread
will pick it up and what it will do is
it will try to invoke the method of the
uh for see for worker thread it doesn't
know whether it's a actual job proxy job
it's a job and it will try to invoke the
job okay but because of this proxy
ultimately this method will get invoked
not the actual one so we have a
pre-processing it goes to the
pre-processing then it will execute the
actual job so it will call super do this
so it's parent actual ual job it will
run it after do it will do
postprocessing
and once it do the post-processing this
is the same thing worker thread will
compute the next time to execute and put
it back to the delay cube okay
so now we have to understand this how
this pre-processing post-processing what
it does internally because with that
itself we could be clear with the uh
shed law
So now I will go with simple step by
step, example by example. Okay. At any
point of time you have a doubt. Pause
it. Go through it again. Okay. I'm going
a little slow. Step one, insert the
proxy job in delay Q. Don't see it now.
Just think if you have watched the
previous uh architecture uh the
scheduleuler distributed part one. If
you have seen that you know that how. So
here
we have enabled at the rate enabled
scheduuling remember and we have a class
and we have put on the method at the
rate scheduled let's say I am doing
fixed rate 5 minutes it is in
millisecond so I am following a fixed
rate at the rate schedule so what
generally used to happen that when you
start the application because of this
enableing it will look for all at the
rate scheduled and it will also put the
first initial put into the delay Q also.
Okay. So that we know
but now here if you see that the same
thing I have enabled the shedlock here.
So here for enabling the shedlock I have
put at the rate enable scheduleuler
lock. Okay shedlock is nothing but the
scheduleuler lock. Add the rate enable
scheduleuler lock. default log at most
for 10 minute we'll come to that later
and below this method the job actual job
earlier we have only add the rate
schedule fixed rate I have also put at
the rate scheduleuler log what is the
name of the job I want to give my job
lock at most for 8 minute lock at least
for 4 minute we'll come to that later
but now what happened here is that
what we have done an integration between
uh you can say that shedlock
and you can say that spring
scheduleuler.
So what happened is that first this
shedlock
okay we have enabled the scheduleuler
log right shed log so it will look for
all the annotation
at the scheduleuler log okay and it will
create a proxy for those
enable scheduleuler log so this is the
purpose of this that it will also create
proxy for those also okay so now let's
say my job so what it will do is it will
create one let's Okay.
Proxy
scheduleuler test class
which will extend our scheduleuler test
and it will also this my job right it
will also provide override this my job.
So that it will create who will create
this enable scheduleuler log. it will uh
you can say that add those uh beans
properly which required for scheduleuler
log. Okay. So internally it scan for all
this shedlock annotation
create a proxy for those and now this
proxy ultimately this enabled
shoulduling put it into the delayed
queue.
Okay.
So when we are using shedlock for
particular scheduleuler job it create a
proxy for that job first and then proxy
job is inserted into the delay.
So that is clear. Now let's take a
insight into what the scheduleuler log
parameter is. So name is my job. So this
is optional again. So if you uh see the
table
in table has this three things name four
things name logged at logged until and
logged by. So see name is this uh the
one [clears throat]
this name
which is optional. If you don't give
this name then it will take out this
class name combination of class name and
this method name it will take out a
create a name itself.
Lock at most for. So this lock at most
for is that uh in this table this lock
until lock until lock at most. So now
till what time you want to keep a lock
on this job. Okay see nothing is
physical lock. You can say that like
like not pessimistic lock. We are
acquiring the lock actual. It's just a
naming. Okay. I'll show you like how it
work in an optimistic manner.
Then we have something called log at
least for. So see this is also optional.
It is not even stored in DB. So if you
have seen the table, we don't have any
column for log at least for this is just
a configuration value. You can say that
uh I'll show you its usage. But consider
for now is that this is the minimum
amount of time lock should be present.
Let's say if your job finish in 3 second
but if you have put and you have put a
lock at least for 1 minute then no
matter if you have finished within 3
second next run cannot be possible
after uh like with this minimum lock
passed.
Consider this in a simple manner. So
whatever the minutes or whatever the
time you have put here lock at least for
okay the next execution or the next
other instance
I will not say execution because uh I
would say that the next instance will
only acquire the log after this time
only. So this is the minimum time
consider that and this is the maximum
time and minimum time is don't even
restore it is just a configuration
value.
Now
lock at most for here is optional. So if
you don't give it here in the at the
enabled scheduleuler lock this is
mandatory default log at most for so it
would be used. So see we have might we
have hundred of scheduleular jobs. It is
possible that for most you forgot to add
log atmos for so it will use this
because I told you that shedlock do not
put any log like pessimistic it all
depend upon
this two columns log at log until so
this is log until is log at most for so
it can it should never be empty so
that's where it is mandatory so this is
the default even if you forgot it here
it will pick the default one. Okay.
Otherwise, if you have added here, this
would be given priority.
So, at till this point of time,
don't worry if you are getting confused
that what is this? At this point of
time, my intention here is that you
understand that
we have a table
which contains certain information about
that who is running the job. Okay, which
instance, which instance is running the
job. First part. Second part is in the
delay Q the job which is entered is the
proxy job not the actual job. Okay. So
and the proxy job I told you that uh has
some pre-processing post-processing and
then it execute the job. So this is main
important at this step one right. Okay.
So
I have also showed you that why at the
rate enabled scheduleuler lock is
mandatory because its purpose is to uh
scan for this at the rate scheduleuler
lock annotation and now it knows that
for this method for this class it has to
create a proxy. Okay. and also it helps
in loading the uh beans for shedlock
related feature.
So you can add a dependency. So here the
first dependency you need is that this
one javacrumbs.shedlock
shedlock is spring and the latest
version you want to pick. So you can say
that it is more like of an integration
between
shedlock
and spring
bootuler.
Okay. So this is the first dependency
you need. Now let's go with an example.
Let's say current time is 8:55.
Okay. And you have a two instance.
Instance one, instance two.
This is a delayed queue and your proxy
job is present which need to be run at
9. Okay. And your currently thread one
is in time weight for let's say 5
minutes because it is 8:55. It need to
be run at 9. 5 minutes. Thread one is in
time weight state.
Similarly, part two, the same scenario.
Job need to be run at 9. Thread one, it
is in time weight state. Worker pool
shedlock is currently empty. And
remember that this name is a primary
key. Okay. So, every job only has one
entry in it.
Now, step two, pick the proxy job from
the delay Q. Now let's say the 9 a.m.
has been done and it's time. So both the
threads in instance one and instance
both the thread got wake up. Pick the
proxy job from this delayed queue both
and both try to execute this proxy job.
Okay. Till now no magic has happened.
Everything like before and this proxy uh
this job has this configuration name is
my job. We have already showed you that
at the rate at the rate scheduleuler
lock has
lock at most for 8 minute lock at least
for 4 minute fixed rate 5 minute that's
the configuration right this one the
same example I'm looking fixed rate is 5
minute and this is the shedlock my job 8
minute 4 minute okay the same thing
so this is the job feature now what it
will do is it will execute it and you
know that it's a proxy job. It will not
execute method first. It will do
pre-processing. So now in
pre-processing, let's go one by one to
the instance one first. So instance one,
what it will do? It will try to acquire
the job. And when it will try to acquire
the job, it check is job name present in
DB currently. No. As this job is
executing for the first time. Similarly
instance 2 is doing the same thing in
parallel in pre-processing it will try
to acquire the job is job name present
in DB currently no as this job is
executing for the first time both now
they both try to insert
into shedlock table and with this all
this thing they have a name okay they
have logged at currently what time it is
logged until we have also specified log
at most for log until and log by
whichever is able to take the log. So
insert into
value is my job now is like current DB
time whatever the current DB time plus 8
minutes because let's say at lock at
most is 8 minute and the pod one
similarly pod 2 is trying to that hey
this is the job I want to acquire the
lease
current DB time current DB time plus 8
minutes that's the max time lock at most
for and part two hey I am the one which
is acquiring the
Now since name is the primary key only
one will get success. Okay only one will
get success. Now let's say that pod one
got success. So pod one entry goes in.
Now part two what will do? Pod two
failed to acquire the job. So it will
skip the execution itself.
What part two will do? Part two will
compute the next runtime for this job.
So we are doing fixed rate. Right? Fixed
rate what is the formula
previous runtime plus fixed rate delay
whatever so previous runtime was when
when it was run 9
and uh fixed rate was I think 5 minutes
so the next it will compute is 9:05
the pod 2 will again put the job into it
delay Q run it at 9:05 till it it is
time weight okay
So instance this got skipped goes into
the sleep state again and this pod one
is still in the running. So
pre-processing is done log is acquired.
Okay.
Now let's stop a bit here and before we
proceed here.
So proxy creation, pre-processing etc
everything is provided by shedlock
library. Okay. So we do not have to
write a single thing
whatever has happened this
pre-processing hey is job name present
in DB yes or no okay and then do this
insert query so these are all present
inside the shedlock libraries itself we
don't have to do anything so proxy is
created by shedlock library
pre-processing code is provided by it
Okay.
So
all we have to worry about is [snorts]
like we also don't have to worry about
this uh insert update queries and all.
Okay. Because shedlock has like
everything provided it even for insert
and update it has provided the wrapper
libraries on all. Okay. So for let's say
if you are using relational database it
has provided JD JDBC template shedlock
provider JDBC template. So this is the
second library which I am using. Okay
let's say if you are using radius to
maintain this table then there is a
radius wrapper.
Okay. So it has different wrappers like
if you are MongoDB it shedlock has
MongoDB wrapper. So now whichever
whichever DB you are using, you need to
use the appropriate wrapper.
See why you need this wrapper? Let's say
I am using relational database. So
that's why I'm using this uh shedlock -
provider - JDBC template. Okay, why I
need this? Because see shedlog need to
perform the DB queries insert queries
update queries and we I don't have to
write these queries or logic all I am
dealing with the annotation at the rate
schedule lock I have provided this hey
this is the job name this is lock atmost
for lock at least for and this is a
fixed rate at the rate schedule but I am
not running any insert query update
query so internally it does okay so
internally it
using this wrapper
and you might be saying hey why does it
need wrapper why can't it simply have
JDBC template itself why it need a
wrapper shedlock provider see this
wrapper is required because they need to
understand the shedlock table so
shedlock table has name log loged until
so that's why a wrapper is required so
it's a very lightweight wrapper which
understand this shedlock table
which has uh like expose certain uh you
can say that interfaces which get the
value out of this like what is the max
lo at most for lock at least for and all
and it just insert into the relational
database through this wrapper internally
this wrapper talk to JDBC only. Okay.
So this is the another dependency you
need apart from your DB whichever DB you
are using MySQL and their proper driver.
So those are not those are your just
like you whatever the DB you are using
you need that dependency that because
those dependency do not come with this.
So you need your DB dependency the
driver dependency this is just a wrapper
whatever the DB you are using it's
wrapper so let me show you here also
that pom.xml
the DB which I am using is uh in memory
one the here I am using S2 DB. So I have
an S2DB. Okay, I have already showed you
in the JPA part like we have worked a
lot with S2.
So this is the this one and this is it
driver. All the shedlock dependency I
have is that uh the shedlock spring
which is like you can say that
integration between shedlock and spring.
All right. and this wrapper
shedlock provider JD JDBC template
because H2 is uh relational database so
that's why I am using JDBC template if
you are using radius use radius wrapper
cool
now another thing which we have to do is
that to this wrapper okay so this
wrapper you can say that it is a log
provider so this is an interface
And then we have a JD JDBC template log
provider radius log provider. This is an
what library which we have added this
one right? JDBC template these are comes
with this class. These classes will come
from this. Okay. So this is an interface
and when you have this
wrapper you are adding this
implementation for this JDBC template
log provider.
If you are adding a radius wrapper so
you are ultimately adding radius locker
lock provider. Okay. So this is
implementation we have to add this
dependency and why this dependency is
required because they understand
they have to write into the DB.
Okay. And again last thing before we
proceed further we have to provide a
bean because see we need to tell the
data source see data source has like DB
URL username password everything so it
need to connect to your DB right so
that's where one configuration in which
you have to provide a bean for this log
provider and currently I am using JDBC
right so JDBC template log provider so
in this on here I am internally it will
use JD JDBC template only and the data
source data source comes [snorts] from
your configuration class so in
application.properties properties you
might be having like URL, username,
password. So those will come into your
data source.
Okay. So this is mostly we have done
into the JPA part like uh okay but here
that's why I stopped a bit to tell you
that yes we need a different dependency
also.
Now let's come back again to our
step three.
So now till step two what we have seen
is that
pod one acquired the lock completed its
pre-processing
and
it started doing execution.
Part two was
not able to acquire the log. So it is
still skip the scheduleuler and it has a
delayed queue which has the next running
at 9:05 and thread is in currently time
weighted state and pod one
currently is doing execution. Now what
the step three is the pod one finishes
the task before next runtime itself say
9:03. So 9:05 was the next execution
time. Consider that. But it finishes at
9:03 itself. What would happen? So
pre-processing of the pod one done. And
after that our shedlock table was like
this log taken at 9 logged until 9:08
because
log at most for is 8 minute log by port
one. This was at the time of
pre-processing.
Invoke real job method done and finished
at 9:03. This is the use case which we
are taking. Now the post-processing what
would happen in the post-processing?
So post-processing what it will do? It
will do this max of
so it will update this lock until column
with this max of
uh whatever the current time it is.
current time whatever the current time
it is or
logged at least for so log I log I took
a log at 9 plus the minimum time I need
to keep it lock for 4 minute 4 so either
so what let's say now is currently what
we example is at 9:03 the job is
finished so current time is 9:03
and The log that is at 9 and log at
least four we have taken is 4 minute so
it's 9:04 so what is the maximum it's
9:04 so it will update this
it update this lock until 9:04
so this is happen in the post-processing
update the column by when you finished
it okay but it just don't simply update
I finished at this time so update it
will Okay, max of the minimum time you
want to keep it lock for
or if already that minimum time is
crossed then what is the maximum time
you finished updated.
Okay. So till now here it is clear pod
one execution. Now what step four pod
one pushes the job back to a delayed
queue with new runtime. So how pod one
will compute the new runtime? Fixed rate
we are following right. the previous
runtime 9 five. So it will put
9:05. Thread one goes into the time
weight state again. Thread 2 is also is
in uh time weight state instance two
with the proxy job that need to be
executed at 9:05.
Shed log current state is that name is
my job logged at 9 logged until 94 log
by spot one. So this is the current last
state and uh let's say earlier this time
is let's say still 9:03 only okay the
same time
now step five 9:05 comes okay now it's
time for both the threads in different
instance to wake up what would happen
they both wake up pick the task from the
their delay queue they start working on
it the same thing happens again
Now both start their pre-processing.
Both try to acquire the job. What it
will do? Is job name present in DB? Yes,
it's already present because now it's
running second time. Okay. So because
see this is job is already present. My
job is already present.
Okay. So now both goes to this step.
Yes. Is job log until expired? Is this
job can be picked? So what it will do?
Current time is 9:05
and the lock until is 9:04. Yes, this
time is already expired means we can
pick this task. Okay. So yes, lock until
9:04. Current time is 9:05. Yes, it is
expired. I can pick it up. Yes, it is
expired. I can pick it up. Both will try
to pick it up. Now both will try to do
an update call. Update this table. Set.
So they are trying to set the lock until
now. Again they are trying to set this.
Okay. So what's the time they will put?
Whatever the current time current time
is 9:05 plus maximum time they want to
lock it for 8 minute.
So they try to lock it for this much
minute. Okay. Where job is my job and
lock until is less than equals to now.
Lock until now is 9:05.
Okay. So currently lo until is 9:04. So
this query is also valid.
And this query is also valid. So shed
log log until now is 95 + 8 913.
Okay. Loged at current time 9:05 log by
pod where name is my job. This one and
log until less than 9:05. So yes it's
9:04. So both will try to acquire the
log.
So DB level update operation is atomic.
Okay. Internally only one will get
execute. Okay. So it's we are not
putting any log. Internally DB is
atomic.
So what it will do is that let's say D
port 2 is going first. So this is going
first. What it will do? It will update
this query will run. So what would
happen?
Log 9005. So log that is now 9:05
logged until
uh 9:05 + 8 913 logged by port 2. So it
update this. Okay, this query runs. Now
port two query get execute. Okay, what
it will try to update the same thing but
what would happen? See it query in the
where clause it has like lock until less
than now. Lock until less than now. now
is 9:05.
So now part 2 has already increased this
time 9:13. So this will get false. So
nothing will happen. No, no update will
happen.
Okay. So pod one is not able to acquire
the
job. So it skip the execution. It will
compute the next runtime. Next runtime
is that previous uh runtime is 9:05 plus
5 minute is the delay. Next runtime is
910.
It will put it into the delay queue and
goes into the time weight state.
Step six, part two is taking too long
time while executing the job. So part
two is still running the job and the
next runtime has come. Now let's say 910
has come. What would happen?
The current state is that it picked the
job 910 and it start executing on it.
Port 2 is already pre-processing done
and it is working. It's still running at
9:010 also it is still running. Okay.
And this has come. So it will try to
acquire the job. Is job name present in
DB? Yes,
we already have a job name. Sorry, we
already have a job name present.
Is job log until expired? So is expired?
So log until is 9:13. Current time is
9:10.
Okay. So is it expired? No, it is not
yet expired. Lock until is 9:30. Current
expired is 9:10. So it is not expired.
So pod one cannot even take the log. So
it will escape it execution.
Okay. And it will compute the next
execution time 910 + 5 9:15. It will put
9:15 goes into the time state
again. Step seven, part two is still
taking two long time while executing the
job. And next execution time has come.
9:15 has come. This is very important.
See this one. Now what would happen? So
part two is still running. Current time
is 9:15.
Port two is pre-processing was done. It
is still working.
Now at 9:15 this has take invoked again
and it start working on it pre-process
try to acquire the job is job name
already present in DB yes so yes job is
present is job until expired so lock
until was 9:13
current time is 9:15 so it is expired
yes it is expired so it is allowed to
take it up so what it will do is it will
update it so it will do update
Update the log until now + 8 minute. So
9:15 + 8 minute 9:23 updated logged at
now 9:15 logged by spod 1. Okay. Where
name is my job log until less than now.
So earlier it was 9:13 now is 9:15. So
this query properly satisfied this
information got updated and it start
working on this. So in shedlock this is
very important what I'm trying to say in
shedlock
two instances still can run the job in
parallel if
the logged until if the logged at most
for is very less time and your job is
taking too long time that's what
happened so that's why we say that give
the maximum log time should be long
enough
right so that any chance of duplicate
run can be avoided
two instances
but if here in this case what happened
is the log time is for 8 minute okay
here in this case
so it was logged until 9:13 but time has
reached 9:15 and because of heavy
loading it is was still working when
9:15 has come so now both the instances
now working okay that It is the only use
case when in shedlock more than one
instance can still run in parallel. This
might interview can ask
now what happened at let's say step 8
pod one is working on this job. Pod two
is finished. Now at 8 9 810 now part two
has finished it. So pre-processing done.
Invoke real job method done. Now
postprocessing. In post-processing I
told you it tried to update this table
with
max of now. Now is 918
comma
log that log that is at what at what
time it logged. Okay, log that plus
logged at least four. Okay, so this is
it will try to update it
but will it be able to update
this query has no impact. So see
whatever the query it will come that
this is the new time but will it be able
to do? No. Because see in the update
query it check where log by is me.
But here if you see the log by is
changed to pod one itself. part one is
already started working on it. So
whatever the
log until time it will compute max of
now comma log that plus log that list
four whatever the time it will compute
those update will not even happen
because log by is pod two and this log
by pod one is already updated by pod
one. Okay. So those post processing is
you can say that it is of uh no use now
because it's already updated.
So part two will compute the next
runtime. Next runtime it will compute.
So it started at 9:05. So it will
compute next runtime 5 910. Hey it is
already missed. Then 910 + 5 9:15. Hey
this is already missed. Then 9:15 + 5
920. This is future because current time
is 9:18. So it is this is future. So
this will put into the delayed Q 920. It
goes into the time vary state
and this goes on goes on goes on.
You got the shedlock.
Okay.
So let's see this first the same code I
am showing you. Okay. So here
pom.xml I have already showed you that
the dependency.
Now in the config I have added let me
zoom it a bit.
In the config I have just provided the
data source JDB JDBC template log
provider and in the
application.properties this data source
infos are all present.
Okay I have written one schema.sql so
that because see I am using h2. H2 is
like as soon as every every time
application startup happen uh the DB
gone. Okay. So I just created uh
schema.sql to create the shedlock table
and this column. Okay. And whenever I
create an application, it will create
this table for me. Okay.
And in the application scheduleuler
application main method one, I have
added this at the rate enabled
scheduleuler lock. This is the default.
I want to keep it for 10 minute. And
this is the scheduleuler. Okay. Uh very
simple. Add the rate schedule fixed
rate. This 60,000 mcond is nothing but a
1 minute. Add the rateuler lock my job
lock at least for 4 minute lock at most
for 8 minute. Okay. And I have just for
testing I have just kept a sleep for
half minute. So now see that what is the
expectation? What would happen?
expectation is that when I start an
application okay so initial delay is
here zero so it will pick as soon as
possible so it will see that's all I
need I I don't have to worry about
pre-processing post-processing
everything is handled by the uh
libraries framework
but as soon as application startup
happen it will create a row in the shed
shedlock table where it will put hey
this is the my
and logged at current time and at most
is 8 minute.
Okay. But my job will get finished
within half minute itself. Okay. And in
the post-processing it will try to
update but it will not update like as
soon as I finished like I let's say I
started at 10 and in half minute I
completed it. It will not so it will
keep the minimum block for 4 minute.
Okay. So we can test it. Let me start an
application.
I started the application. Let's see
this.
Connect it. Check the table. So here
currently
job is running at 14 uh logged at 141
1736. You can say that this is a current
time logged until 8 minute, right? So 17
+ 8. So 14 25 36. So this is current
situation. Now after what would happen
is
thread do.lip this will
wait for half minute and job execution
will finish its job. Now in the
post-processing it will try to update
the max of
this and
147 + 4. So it will update to 1421.
Let's refresh it. 1421.
Okay. The same thing like whatever we
have done right. uh
post-processing part, right? The same
thing. It runs the same query. No magic.
[snorts]
Cool.
Now here I want to show you that one
last thing. Huh? But last not the least.
If you want custom table name and column
name, see currently
we are using wrapper JDBC template
shedlo wrapper and by default it knows
that okay the table name would be this
this would be the column name because it
is internally doing insert update
operation. But what if I create a table
name something like shed uh shed how it
would know whether I have created this
name? What if I give some different
name? So if you want to use some custom
table name column name in this bean
creation of log provider you just need
to update that hey the table name is
this these are the column name okay I
kept it last because generally for
shedlock the table name nobody changes
it they try to keep it same but anyway
if your uh business logic demand
different name and while the bean
creation just update the table name and
column name also
okay and with this the shedlock is
completed.
I tried to explain with different
stepbystep diagrams and all because this
is very hard to explain like uh what
happening new table log that logged
until many says that it follows
optimistic but how optimistic how come
lo is not involved so now you able to
get it what exactly happened in
pre-processing post-processing
uh like how it actually takes care of
this all optimistic uh concurrency
manner okay any doubt let me know we
discuss in comment section. But with
this distributed scheduleuler is
complete. Okay guys, thank you.